The following was recorded live at the 2026 Parish Life Conference of the Antiochian Orthodox
Diasis of Miami and the Southeast, held June 10th through 13th in Springdale, Arkansas.
We begin with a short presentation, followed by a live Q&A with a gathered audience.
Father Steven told me that I should juggle or something while he was
stepping out for a moment so you guys missed the juggling I was doing it. He had
five chainsaws it was really impressive. Don't know how you missed it. The hotel
hotel provided those chainsaws actually. They came with a room. Why they had
chainsaws we don't know. Circula saw sure. I'm waiting for people. Maybe even a
jigsaw perhaps. I think we lost them with that series of jokes it was not
This is the last video.
We'll see you next time.
Bye.
At some point it wasn't funny anymore.
The problem with the circular saw is they usually have cords.
It's a trick to juggling them even harder
Without cutting the cord
So like yesterday we are gonna go till about 15 minutes before Vespers and
This afternoon father Stephen has promised us a presentation
About the habitats of rodents mice in particular I'll get there
I know that's what you came to hear.
right who came to hear the mouse habitat.
Yes, don't like came walk to the room,
like came to Arkansas.
That's right.
To hear me talk about mouse habitat.
So don't disappoint them, Father.
OK.
I inevitably will.
So this actually all started with me having a conversation
with a well-known in Europe, post-Marxist soci-
theologist about the works of Simone Vé in pre-war France.
And she asked me, what does Christianity have to say about alienation?
The TV series?
No, not the TV series.
Or the film with James Conn.
No, she meant alienation in the...
Marxist sense, which to really shorthand, really, really, really shorthand, is the idea that
at a certain point in culture, for Marx based on capitalism, but based on whatever, people's
relationships with each other get replaced by relationships with things.
So I no longer have a relationship with a person, I have a relationship with a thing.
So
So just one quick example of that.
If someone roll the clock back, if someone is a furniture maker, they make a piece of furniture
by hand, they make a chair, and they give it to me.
I have that chair now.
And even though that chair is an object, that object is part of a relationship with a
person.
I know the person who made it, I know the person who gave it to me.
It's a gift I received from that person.
the up.
is part of a relationship between people.
Right?
And then if I take that chair and I hand it down to someone
and they hand it down to the next generation,
then it's, oh, this is the chair I inherited from my grandfather.
And it's part of the relationship with your every time
you look at it, right?
Now, no offense to anyone here who's local.
But if I go and buy a chair at Walmart,
That share is not part of a relationship between me.
in anyone in particular.
It's just a chair, right?
It's just a chair.
And even if it's my favorite chair,
it's just a relationship between me and a chair.
There's no human on the other end of it.
So let's just an example, but that dynamic has affected
pretty much every area of human life at this point.
Most people's jobs in their work life.
You're not working at old man so-and-so's store.
You're not working.
You may have a boss who's directly over you,
but they're also just an employee of sort of this nameless,
faceless, corporate thing.
Right.
And most people nowadays are going to work for a paycheck,
because they have certain, they have to have food, shelter, housing,
The way you get the money for that is by working.
right. And among younger people, younger people here are probably aware of this, especially
Zoomers. There is now this great movement to minimize work. A lot of people in that generation,
including some I know, it's not about, oh, I'm going to find a career, I'm going to work
hard, I'm going to advance in that career, I'm going to do this and that. It's, okay,
Here's how much money I need to live.
I will work.
exactly enough to get that and then stop.
And because they're just sort of stopping at that point,
it's not like the rest of their time
they're going out and having adventures.
They're sitting at home in front of a screen,
which again is a relationship with an object,
not with another person.
And even if you might wanna say to me
that while sometimes they're having a relationship
another person through that screen.
I would point out to you in how many cases the person who they think they're relating to
on the other side of the screen turns out to not be that person at all.
That it really is a relationship with the object.
And now they're not even attempting that so much because now we have AI that you can
have a relationship with and talk to.
So this is the level of alienation that we've really reached.
and this got super hyper accelerated by COVID.
and the lockdowns, and the breakdown in in-person human relationships.
So what does Christianity in particularly Orthodox Christianity have to say about this?
I believe Orthodox Christianity, and by that I mean our parishes, actual in-person in the parish, Orthodox Christianity, the liturgy, the community.
I think speaks to this in modern American culture in three pretty unique ways.
there's nobody else who's offering, really offering these answers.
And to talk about the first two, we have to talk about universe 25.
And I know you don't know what that is probably.
Well, there's one person here who I think probably knows what that is.
But otherwise, most people don't know what that is.
I'm not talking about Earth 25 in either Marvel or DC comics.
That exists in both of them.
Sorry.
We can talk about that later.
Universe 25 was an experiment done by a fellow named John B. Calhoun.
Universe 25 was a mouse habitat. See, I got there.
And as you might guess from the name, it was the 25th such experiment that he ran.
And it was called Universe 25 because he created this whole world.
for the mice, in which they lived, fed, operated as a mouse community. I don't
know what a group of mice is called, a pack. I don't know. Rat pack.
Rat pack. Yeah, so maybe a pack. But Universe 25 in particular was an attempt to
create mouse utopia because he wanted, he was trying to study the effects of
of overpopulation.
But there are some other things we learn.
in the process.
So in universe 25 in this mouse utopia,
the mice had all the food they wanted,
all the water they wanted.
They didn't have to go look for it.
It was just given to them.
They were supplied with everything, bedding, right?
Everything that a mouse could possibly want in life
was just given to them.
Within two years, the population had ballooned
to like 12 times its original size.
But then another two
years the last mouse died.
So mouse utopia turned into a nightmare.
The first lesson I think we can learn, and this one comes from universe 25, is that part
of mouse behavior is that male mice will compete with each other, meaning sort of fight
wrestle, tussle, in order to get the attention of female mice.
This is sort of normal animal behavior.
When that happens, there's a winner and a loser.
The winner finds a mate, the loser normally leaves.
Leaves that pack, leaves that group of mice, and goes and finds another one and starts over.
You can't do that in universe 25, because it's contained.
And so the mice who ended up being losers had to...
stay in this vows community and sort of bear their shame and their status forever.
These mice have instantly became violent.
They would attack other mice.
They would attack the young of other mice.
I think there's a lesson here, and I think this is something we can observe in human behavior
with this alienation.
We've created a culture now where once you are shamed, once you are canceled, once you
or ostracized there is no escape.
It will follow you forever.
We call this accountability.
Something you tweeted, something you said,
something you did 12 years ago,
it doesn't matter who you've become now,
it doesn't matter what you've done since.
It will be brought back up.
It will be used to try to keep you from starting over.
And when we force people to live with their shame,
with no escape.
What happens to them?
They start to act out,
they start to engage in fringe behavior, sometimes even violence like those mice.
We're not that different.
The Orthodox Church is the one place left in American culture where,
if we're doing it right in our communities,
someone can come in and start again.
If we really believe, for example, in the sacrament of baptism,
If we really believe
that a person who comes into our church
and is received into the church dies.
The person they were as dead is gone.
All of that past history is deleted
and they get a new start as a new person,
a lot of times with a new name.
If we really believe in that
and we really practice that in our communities,
then this is the one place
We're an alienated angry
We shame to person can begin again and can escape their past.
That requires a couple of things of us.
It requires that we don't keep bringing that past up.
It requires that we don't decide that there's a group of people who aren't welcome in our
parish, because we don't like their politics one way or the other.
We don't like how they've behaved in the past one way or the other.
like a
us in some way. If we're welcoming them as we should, an orthodox parish is the one place
where they have that chance. Second thing, also from universe 25. One of the reasons
why the whole thing collapsed is that when everything the mice needed was provided for
them and there was no work to do. The mice who would normally go and scout for food.
didn't go scout for food.
The ones who would protect the group
didn't have anything to protect the group from.
All of the social roles within this pack of mice collapsed.
Every mouse was the same, and they all had nothing to do.
There was no hierarchy, no structure.
And it got to the point where even mice were able to realize
that their life was...
basically purposeless, my started dying deaths of despair in
universe 25. They stopped eating, they stopped drinking, and
literally let themselves die. We can look out at our society, we
could see the same thing has happened. Social roles, everything
possible has been done to erode them. Even at the level of
male female. Let alone any kind of hierarchy.
structure or purpose or identity.
Everything has been pushed toward equality and therefore
interchangeability.
And so our world is full of people who have no sense of purpose.
That's why they think that working 20 hours a week to pay the
bare minimum, what's the point of more than that?
You have been statistics about deaths of despair.
in this country, it's frightening.
Deaths of despair includes people just ending their own lives,
but it also includes drug overdoses, addiction rates.
As we talked about a little bit yesterday,
an Orthodox parish could be the one place
where someone, no matter what they do for a living,
no matter what their talents are or aren't,
can be given a sense of purpose.
Can have a community in which they contribute something
that is uniquely theirs.
that only they can contribute to that community where they're appreciated for it.
And feel a sense of purpose about it.
Maybe they're living in a cubicle,
or working in a cubicle and living in a little box apartment.
It's completely interchangeable, and they're a drone.
But when they go to church, they're a part of a community that loves them
and cares about them and appreciates what they bring to the table.
Again, if we're doing it right in our...
communities. This is an incredible opportunity for people out in our culture who are completely
alienated otherwise. The third thing I think we have to contribute
uniquely, this doesn't involve the mouse habitat. So, thus far for mouse habitats. And this
has to do with something that a fellow, another sociologist named Christopher Lash wrote in
a book called, uh...
the culture of narcissism.
I was written some years ago
about the way American culture was headed.
Talking about how our culture has shifted
so that people think about themselves
in their lives in this very narcissistic way.
The purpose of my life,
the purpose of what I do,
the purpose of my work,
the purpose of anything I do
is to bring myself happiness.
Right, to bring myself happiness.
personally. And he could trust this with the way people historically live their lives,
and the way people in a lot of other countries still live their lives, which is that, and
this is his phrase, people see their lives as a thread stretched between their parents
and their children. That's what their life is. The first half of their life is receiving
from their parents, receiving their culture, receiving their knowledge, receiving their wisdom.
being formed and shaped by that.
And then the second half of their life is
passing that down to the next generation.
So our lives are not just
this thing by itself but are this connection,
this generational connection. And people in our culture don't experience this anymore.
Because
Christopher Lash wrote that book.
I think almost 40 years ago now, meaning our culture headed that way a long time ago.
And so the young people today were unfortunately raised by parents who that's how they looked
at their lives.
And if your parents look at their life as about their own happiness, that means they're
not passing anything on to you.
And that means you don't have anything to pass.
on to the next generation. And so you're dislocated. You fall into the idea that your life should
be about making yourself happy just by default, because that's what everyone else seems to be doing.
And increasingly, as we've just been talking about, people are not happy.
And they aren't finding ways out in the world in our culture to make themselves happy, at least for
very long. Should he mob be
in terms of that way of life, the Orthodox Church
is incredibly uniquely situated now,
even among religious groups in the United States
to answer that issue, that generational issue.
Because I'm telling you right now,
if you go to any evangelical church in this country,
it looks nothing like it looked like a generation ago.
Any been further from the generation before that
and even further from the generation before that.
You can go to Roman Catholic churches in this country and they look nothing like they looked
to generation ago and absolutely nothing like they looked before Vatican II.
Whereas the Orthodox Church, you can go to one of our Orthodox parishes today and it looks
and the liturgy is exactly like it was except maybe for language a generation ago and a generation
before that and a generation before that.
So the Orthodox Church and the Orthodox community is still a place that a person can come to
and as a new Orthodox Christian be formed by it.
Receive something that has been handed down for generations.
Receive wisdom, receive understanding, receive tradition, receive a culture, and then can
hope to pass that on to their children and to the
next generation. But once again we have to be serious about that. It requires that those
of us who are older, I find myself getting increasingly old, fancy that, right? We have
to be serious about passing on what we've learned and what we've come to understand to
the newcomers, to the next generation. And the people who are newcomers, or newer
and cameras.
There's a lot of the people here who are young Orthodox Christians have to become serious
about receiving.
Not about figuring out for yourself from books, but receiving, forming relationships with
the people who have been formed by the Orthodox community and receiving that yourself, so
that you'll be ready to pass it on to the next generation when your time comes.
So 25 years ago, I was brand new to the Orthodox Church. I was having to receive.
Now I'm in my fifties.
Now it's pass on, right?
And some of you sitting here right now,
you may have been Christmas-made like a month ago or something.
The time will come.
What has happened to me will happen to you.
You will, Lord willing, God grant you all many years,
you will be an old man or an old woman.
And you will have things to pass on if you receive them.
Have you spent your time now receiving them?
So I think all three of those things form a kind of treatment.
Maybe even a cure to the alienation of modern society.
All of us have a role to play in our communities
in making that treatment, making those things
available to the people who show up at the door,
who are alienated and disaffected and frustrated,
and angry and confused.
and don't even know how to have a conversation with a person
and have weird views of things
and extreme politics they got off the internet
and all that stuff, right?
They desperately need what we have to offer
and if we're serious about having it on offer
and giving it to them,
then I think Orthodox Christianity
is what Christianity has to say about alienation.
So questions.
Come on down.
on down.
Ancient Near Eastern texts such as the Bale Cycle portray the pagan god Bale as a rebel.
The hero of a revolution worshipped and glorified for his long string of victories.
In the Bale Book, a biography of the devil, Father Stephen the Young shows that the Hebrew
scriptures consciously turn the Bale story on its head.
And picking him is a failed and defeated rabble who nonetheless tries to steal the glory.
that belongs to Almighty God.
From these scriptures, the figure of the devil
emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father Stephen works through the old and new testament
passages that refer to various bail stories,
and he surveys bail worship through followers' beliefs,
religious practices, and liturgical life
to show that the figures of bail in the devil,
the Prince of demons, are one in the same.
You can find the bail book at store.hentfaith.com.
That's store.hentfaith.com.
That's why we have these two mics here.
And see I did talk about mouse habitats.
Yeah, I was joking yesterday.
I did give it a 50-50 actually.
Hello.
Hello, fathers.
This may actually tie in a bit more with what you talked about yesterday.
Sorry.
Father Andrew, you talked about the need for access to
Orthodox worship and life through like a language that people understand.
So I come from a background working in Deaf Ministry from the Protestant world.
So that's Deaf with an F, not a TH.
And some people sometimes miss here ironically.
So I'm a bit familiar with things like the Orthodox Christian Deaf Association.
But I'd like to know maybe from your perspective or experience.
If the Orthodox Church has some kind of vision or plans for incorporating deaf people into Orthodox worship and life,
whether that is interpreting or there's possibility of like signed liturgies
or there's possibility of deaf clergy or anything like that.
Yeah. I mean, this is definitely not my expertise, but I am aware of at least a little bit of children's content that has been made on YouTube
with a
someone who's doing it with signs along the way.
But yeah, I don't know.
My experience has always been that when there's a new group
of people that the church needs to minister to,
that the people that tend to be out in the front of that
are the first people from that group who come into the church.
Right?
And so, for instance, one of the, actually, one of the less known,
but I think should be better known statistics
about orthodoxy in America right now,
is that 14% of orthodox Christians in America are Hispanic.
which is a big surprise, I think, to a lot of people, seeing some heads nodding.
And the people that have been really in the forefront of working with Hispanics have been
Hispanic clergy and other Hispanics that have become Orthodox.
So, I mean, I'm not, I know some people that are involved with the Orthodox Christian
Deaf Association. And what I would just simply do is encourage them and say, like, look,
this is your mission, you know, because most of us don't have the skills to do that, I certainly
I'm trying to imagine deaf clergy.
It would be a difficult thing to do because it would be hard to serve the liturgy if you can't hear.
Because so much of what's going on in the liturgy is oral.
So I don't know how that would be possible.
But I'm not a bishop, so fortunately no one is asking me to make any decisions about that.
But there's definitely room for a lot of this ministry and it's important, you know.
That's what I have to say about it. I don't have a lot of...
of a lot to offer in that regard.
You father?
I don't have a ton, but I have been in a situation
multiple times as a priest where I've had a deaf parishioner
present, and I've had someone sign translating
like my homoly and some other pieces of the liturgy.
So I think at least that, I think one of the things
you have to do as a priest is when you
You get the blessing of having someone in your parish who has a little different issues
than maybe other people.
It's actually a blessing to get to figure out how to help minister to them most effectively.
It kind of helps everybody in the parish in doing that because it causes them to have to
think in a way that they normally don't think.
Things they normally take for granted, they now have to think about.
And so...
At a very basic level, I would hope that every priest in our
anxieties would, if they have a deaf parishioner, would start thinking in that direction.
We need to find someone who knows ASL, we need to have translation going on.
And how do we do that in a way that's not disruptive, but
that's also helpful to the person.
And I think those local solutions are relatively usually easy to do right in the sense of,
doing with
I think that's the place to start.
And then as things progress, I think, yeah,
it goes above our pay grade to the bishops, right?
It's just bigger, larger issues.
I was agreeing with everything you were saying about people
coming into the church and getting them involved.
But what about the people that are not coming into the church?
that was there before and for some reason they...
left, how do you get them back?
I mean, I have a son right now
that he claims he's going to a church in California,
but not in North of Dr. Church.
And to me, he's not going to a church.
So how do you get the other people in our neighborhood
and stuff like that?
Since we aren't going knocking on doors
like some of the other places,
we don't
I have really an evangelism committee going out
and trying to recruit people.
We just wait for them to come.
I'm wondering if there should be something
else added to that.
Yeah, so that's two groups of people.
And I think that the approach to each of those groups
is a little bit different.
If I may say so without sounding too ridiculous,
where are the evangelism committee?
Not just the two?
Yeah, you have to be...
We were elected to that committee by the way.
Yeah, yeah, pointed.
Pointed.
I do not just the two of us, but right now,
at this moment in Orthodox history in America,
the vast majority of evangelism is being done through media.
The reason why people are showing up at the church
is almost all of them have had some kind of encounter
with Orthodoxy through the internet
before they show up, which is how they even heard about us
to begin with.
But nonetheless, I think parishes do have a duty
to their surrounding.
neighborhoods. And I mean if you put a big signboard out
front saying we're going to have a big presentation. This was the way this is the way that in the 1980s and the 90s, if you
those of you who are around that long, remember Orthodox evangelism was being encouraged. Like how a big event bring a
speaker in, you know, hand out contact cards. This was literally in the handbook of evangelism that the Archdiocese
published right when the Department of Visions Evangelism was first formed in 1987 when the former EOC was brought
And
the Orthodox Church.
I remember reading through those, yes, you were there, yes.
So I remember reading through that handbook and so forth.
And most of those techniques would not do anything now,
because people, they see a million billboards and signs
and so forth.
And as Father mentioned, a lot of people
just did home all the time.
So we have to take a different approach.
But I think that the way to connect with our immediate
neighborhoods is probably to offer them some kind of service,
something that will help to meet their needs.
And
not in a bait and switch way.
Like, come on down to have a free meal
and oh, by the way, have you thought about where you would go
if you died tonight?
You know, let's not do that, okay?
Let's not be manipulative, but just to care for them,
to love them in a practical way.
I mean, with regards to the first group
that you mentioned, sir, about the people who have left
and are not back, the first thing I'll say about that
is I think it depends a great deal from person to person
as to how to succeed in doing that.
but I'll also tell you.
So I served 13 years in parish ministry before I started doing what I do now.
And at the beginning of my time as a pastor, there were a number of people in the parish who came to me
and essentially asked this question. They said, you know, there's these people that used to be here and they're not here anymore.
And then occasionally they would say, well, they were here until you came, you know, just as a point in time to market when it stopped.
You know, father, you need to go get...
got them. And, you know, I was a young priest and I was trying to love everybody. And I thought
to myself, okay, well, these people belong to the parish, they're in the directory, you
know. So, I'm going to put out the effort to do that. So, I emailed them all, if I had an
email address for them. I sent them all letters to their house. I called them all on the phone.
I even scheduled house busings and went to their front door and knocked on the front door.
And if they weren't home where they didn't answer the door, which happened at least once because I could hear movement inside
I left them a note and I did that with every single word of these individuals and families
and the number of people that responded to that was exactly
zero
And I went back to the your family and friends who had you know told me that I need to go get them
And I said well, this is what happened, you know
email them. I sent them a letter. I called them in the
I knocked on the door, no response.
Do you have any other suggestions for what I could do?
And they didn't.
And I said, here's my suggestion.
Like, that's your brother, that's your uncle,
that's your cousin, you know, whoever.
I bet you they will listen to you
before they will listen to me.
Which may not be the, I mean, they may not listen.
This is why I think it's particular
to the individual person.
But I think that when people leave,
or drift away is what happens in most cases.
Often it's because there's been some kind of change in life.
A lot of people, for instance, when they moved to a new city,
stop going to church because they just never picked up
the habit, which is why many college students,
why they work so hard to grab them when they arrive at college
because they're in a new place and often the habit
just disappears.
And mom and dad are not making them go anymore.
Sometimes there's been something that's happened in the parish.
Sometimes people, if there's a new priest,
they just don't like the new priest.
Or maybe he's a jerk or a loser or untalented,
can't sing well.
They're talking about me.
Can't preach.
I'm right here.
It's so rude.
Can I tell a slightly less flattering story
about our common job?
Yeah.
OK.
So one thing that a lot of people don't know
is that my first two years in pastoral ministry,
I served as the assistant pass.
at our cathedral in Charleston, West Virginia.
St. George Cathedral in Charleston, West Virginia.
And then as I was on my way out,
three weeks before I was being transferred
to become a pastor, Father Stephen was brought in.
Which as far as we know is when we met,
it might have been before that, but no,
we met before that.
We did, okay, okay.
That's when I remember.
You just over remember.
I don't remember, okay.
And I-
I'm sorry to make an impression, I guess.
Actually the first time I met my wife,
neither one of us remember it happening at all.
Yeah, it was zero impression on each other.
was lead.
I did not eat in the basement of the Antiochian village
and you were rambling about Archbishop of Timeo's Ophatia.
Okay.
So you were kind of distracted from everyone else in the room.
That sounds like a true story.
Yes.
But anyway, I remember, I think you're the one who told me
about this, you know, surely after Father Stephen arrived here.
So at that parish at the time, they would have a practice
that you could drop questions in a box
and then they would get published in the bulletin.
and the senior priest would answer the question.
And one of the questions that arrived,
you know what I'm gonna say, right?
And I think so.
Okay, one of the questions that arrived
shortly after Father Stephen took up
the post as the assistant pastor was,
are priests required to take voice lessons?
It's true.
This is a long family tradition.
My grandfather was thrown out of the church choir
for not being able to sing.
My father was told he could stay at the church choir
that he should just mouth it.
So, wow.
When I was coming into the Orthodox Church,
and he saw us first, I had been preaching
in Protestant churches, and so he saw us
for a Orthodox liturgy, and he said to be Eudiot,
because we're Dutch family.
He said, Eudiot, you can preach OK,
and you can't carry a tune into bucket.
So you join a church where they have a five-minute sermon,
and they sing everything.
Like, what is wrong with you?
So
Yeah.
But the thing that I learned from that pastoral experience
was that there were also a bunch of people standing there
with their hands open, ready to receive something
that I wasn't giving them because I was spending a lot of time
trying to chase people that didn't want to be there.
Which of course is very painful if that's
your friends or your family that they're not there.
But if someone doesn't want to be there,
it doesn't really matter how hard you try to convince them.
They're not going to do it.
it's like
You know guys when you're in middle school or high school and there's this girl you were really into and she was just not into you
It didn't matter how hard you chased her or bugged her or passed her notes in class
I don't know people do that anymore. Do they do that anymore?
She just she just wasn't into you, you know and
Trauma is coming out
But you know that's that's the way that it can be so I think that what needs to happen is
for an interview.
to come back to church is they need to see that they need Christ.
And usually they can't see that by someone telling them that.
But what we can do with folks that are in that situation,
in particular to them, the relationships that they're in,
is number one, we can ensure that they must pray very earnestly for them.
If we really care about their salvation, we have to pray for them very earnestly.
And know that as one of the saints have said,
every time you pray for someone God
them a good thought, which is such a comforting thing to know, but also to love them in a way
that's practical and direct because the people, people's experience, if you want people to
meet Christ, he sent you, you're the one, right? And when it comes to family members, it can
be very difficult because you've got years and years of relationship and maybe who knows where
where the relationship is, but with God, all things truly are possible.
And I have seen people come back.
You know, they say that amongst Orthodox Christians in America, there's so-called cradles and converts
and reverts and retreads, retreads are former clergy that became Orthodox clergy.
So there are reverts.
There are people that it becomes real again for them.
But it may be that they need to spend some time in the desert so that it becomes clear
to them that they need Christ.
That's what I have.
I'll just say real quick so that Father Hunts can ask me whatever Zinger he's got.
The, you know, a lot of folks act like the Orthodox media stuff is a new thing, but there
were a lot of parishes going back who were putting their services on public access cable,
you know, on TV, on local TV stations on the radio back of the day.
The main difference is that...
you know, in the past, someone watching it who is getting drunk and cussing at the screen
didn't have a comment section to go and weigh in.
So don't read the comments.
Never.
That's the.
Go ahead, Father Hans.
This was for you, Father Steven.
I think what you're talking about, the honesty, existential angst and the cultural decline
and everything is really profound.
I don't hear it much in the church.
But I think you hit something really key.
And I agree with you 100% because
has been my experience.
This is why the people are coming in,
especially the young men.
The church by and large doesn't quite understand
the depth of it yet, but I think it will.
I think it's impatient with it sometimes
because of it's a shadow understanding
of what's really going on culturally
and what's going on in their hearts.
It's gonna necessitate a deepening
of the spiritual life in the church as well.
Because this is going to, it's going to, it's going to compel a change because I'm with you.
I think this is going to continue and I'm 100% agree with you when you said that there's only one place left
and that's the Orthodox Church. There's nothing left in the culture.
The other Christian communions, whatever you want to call them, are kind of in a functional, fungely collapsed.
They're not going to be able to address this.
But it's going to compel a change in these
spiritual life of our parishes as well and it's deeper than just mere accommodation.
So given what you've said, I'm presuming here, you've already thought about that and I
would love to hear some of your ideas and reflections on that.
Absolutely. Yeah, so I think some of that impatience comes from if you're in the church.
Hopefully you're already reconnected in ways that the person walking in for the first time isn't.
And so we take things for granted.
Or you're from a previous generation that didn't get quite as alienated in the first place.
Because I've had that experience where you get somebody showing up at the church
who literally doesn't know how to walk up and talk to another person.
person. They don't know what to say. They don't-
know how to start, they don't know where coffee hours just terrifying.
We say stay for coffee hour, have a good time, get some food.
That to them is like, hey, would you like to meet the rabbit dog we keep out back?
That's super hard for them.
It's very easy for those of us who are further along and are connected to look at me,
What's wrong with that guy?
You know, I think that's like that kind of thing is where some of that impatience and
stuff comes from.
But honestly, we're just talking about the main theme of every book of the New Testament.
We're talking about Christian love.
We're talking about actually loving people.
It really is Christian love when it's someone you don't like.
You can love someone without liking them.
You can love someone even though it's tough to love them.
That's why we're friends, Father.
Yes.
I know.
It's improving me by loving someone such as you.
Whereas I am a delight until you just naturally fell into my orbit.
But no, actual love and actual compassion.
This is one of my favorite recent quotes.
Right after WrestleMania this year, Roman Reigns, who's probably the greatest professional
wrestler of our era, said this amazing quote in an interview after his match.
He said, everybody wants you to do good, but not better than them.
And I was like, that's perfect.
Right.
wants you to kind of be okay but not doing better than
them. That's where you enter into the realm of Christian love. What's something good
happens for someone else? When you see them succeeding, when you see them reconnecting,
when you see them thriving, you rejoice more about that than if it happened to you.
You would rather see it happen to them than happen to you.
This is the greatest statements of love in the Scripture. There's two of them. One is Moses
than one is St. Paul.
When each of them
say, I would rather be cut off, blotted out of the book of life, go to eternal hell
if it would mean that these people, these people who don't like me, these people who hate
me, who say nasty things about me. In Moses's case, who have tried to kill me, I would rather
go to hell than see them perish. I have not achieved that level of love for anybody, if I'm honest.
honest, right?
but that's Christian love.
So when you look at those people who are coming in,
rather than seeing the state they're in right now,
love is wanting nothing else
but to see them thrive, grow, reconnect,
all of those things.
That becomes your goal.
And the love when they receive it heals them
from the
the
deleterious effects, like a logical, emotional spiritual of that isolation, of that
onks, it heals them.
There's no other place for healing for them except the church.
Yeah.
I would like to dub to you a lot for that a little bit and say that, you know, the way
that the place that most of us at least have the opportunity to learn that kind of law
is within our families.
most marriages start.
with a strong sense of both people feeling they're receiving something great from the other person.
And those who've been married, you know, more than a few years know that that feeling does not persist on that level for the whole marriage.
It can kind of come and go.
Except for my marriage, this year.
Except for Father Stevenson.
America's sweet heart.
Exactly.
You know.
but that you're eventually offered the opportunity
with your wife, your husband, but then also with your children.
children, actually in a sense greater with your children in some ways, to give love and
not to receive anything back, which is what actual real love in its pure form really
is.
Like Christ died for us while we were at sinners.
Christ did to say, look, if you do the following things, I will die for you.
He died for us while we were at sinners.
And this is really very, very difficult of course.
to love another person and to bury your own need,
to be loved, to be paid back, to be whatever.
I mean, God willing, there is a mutuality
in all those relationships.
God willing, that's the ideal.
But real love always gives without expecting in return.
And I think this is one of the reasons
that we need to.
to work so much on our marriages and our parenting
and so forth so that when someone comes to the parish,
we can become their mothers and fathers and brothers
and sisters in more than just a metaphorical sense
in an actually analogical sense,
that it functions in a way similar to the way
that we have learned that kind of love
within our families.
the best
advice I've ever heard about marriage and it would be seem obvious about parenting
is don't keep score.
I remember when my first child was born, I thought to myself, there is nothing this person
can do for me.
We have to do everything for this person because that's when you're supposed to have
a tiny little baby, that's just the way that it is.
Their life depends on you.
That's actually a really amazing realization to have.
And I think that we need to kind of apply that to more of our relationships, actually.
Also, once your kids are teenagers anymore, they'll start to get back a little bit.
Well, I'll leave it to you to let them know that.
Okay.
Father's blessed. Thank you so much for the talk, Barry Fruple.
I'm a millennial, not a Zoomer, but just to speak to your topic of having relationships with screens and all that,
like starting with...
my generation, we were kind of fed this idea that our opinions are so important and every
thought has to be expressed online specifically. So coming into the church, it's real easy
to fall in love with all the richness of the faith. And I think there's a big temptation
for new converts to like start a podcast or a YouTube channel about the faith. And I
I think that's like a big attempt.
So, provided that you are in the church and living the life of the church, the best that
you can, what would you say to deal with that temptation, to take that zeal and go online
and start to make content?
I get this question a lot.
I mean, I think the first thing is like, no.
Um
You know, it's one thing, of course,
to talk about your faith with other people
through the internet.
You know, to say, this is my experience, you know,
or to whatever it might be.
But it's another thing to put a camera on and a mic on
and say, let me tell you something.
Even if it's just, let me tell you
about my own personal journey or whatever.
I know full well that the vast majority of people
who do that do that with good intentions.
There are some.
I'm pretty sure that's not the case.
I've asked for it to do it with good intentions.
But here's the thing, especially when you're really new in the faith.
When you say, look at me and listen to my journey, I just have to say the very hard thing, which
is why is your journey so important?
Everyone needs to know it.
That it needs to be put out there for people that you don't know to hear it.
It's one thing for you to tell that to your friends.
but it's another thing entirely for you.
to make it a public thing, right?
And I waited for years and years before I started talking
about my own particular experiences
becoming Orthodox, even after I was doing lots of public stuff.
I still prefer not to.
But yeah, I think it's dangerous because there
is an immediate gratification that comes when you get clicks
and views, and in some cases, actual checks in the mail.
And I just remember, you know,
what's her name, Sally Field, you know,
at the awards it was, she was like,
you like me, you really, really like me.
Like that's kind of what YouTube, in many cases,
is kind of about.
It's people that want to be liked,
which is a completely understandable human need,
but when it's through, and this is actually
a really important concept that I think we all need
to grasp a hold of these days,
when it's through a parasocial relationship,
then there's a fundamental distortion in it.
Right? So if you don't know what that word is, I had someone come up to me yesterday, I had
never met him before, and he said to me, I really feel like I know you. And I said, you
have a parasocial relationship with me because I didn't know him. And a parasocial relationship
is when you have the feeling of knowing somebody because you've watched them on the screen
or listened to them or whatever it might be, and you don't actually know them, it's not
mutual, right?
And another big danger in that, of course,
is that parasolial relationships are
had with figures who you don't know them.
What you know is the version of them
that they are putting out there for everybody else.
Right?
So I do a lot of podcasts and some include talking
about my life.
I don't talk about everything in my life.
I talk about certain things in my life.
So what you get is a selection.
What you get is a curated sample.
Even the person you're listening to right now
very different than the person that my wife knows.
You know, it's different than the person and the father's because we have offline conversations.
You should hear them.
Actually, you never get to hear that.
And so when someone goes, when someone's new to the faith and they say, turn on a camera,
turn on a mic, or start writing a blog, whatever, and say, everybody follow me on my journey,
what they're doing is creating this parasocial relationship.
And it actually does go both ways.
The first the creator has a pair of social relationships with a group.
that they don't know, but they see signs of them, they see thumbs up, they see angry reacts,
they see comments, they see usernames that are not their names.
So it's a very mediated, alienated set of relationships that has a lot of problems
to it, right?
And within the people that I work with, we often have conversations about this because
We're working on the internet and so we're
trying to figure out ways to work there in a responsible way that is beneficial to the
church and doesn't simply feed all of the kind of pathologies that exist because of what's
going on there. Even despite all the kind of dark things I just said, I still believe that
we need to have missionaries working on the internet because this is where people are
going to encounter our faith and by God's grace that's what we're trying to do.
I think that it's especially someone that's new.
It's fine to talk with other people through the internet about your faith, but when you make it about yourself
Then you have a big problem. I mean
I've literally just last couple days
I have a priest come to me and say father. I have two YouTubers in my parish. What should I do?
It's true true story and
You know in one case it was a person who is making at least some of their living on YouTube before they came to the church so you would be asking them
To set aside some of their income
And I think that's what we need.
need to do for the sake of people's souls, actually, because it is a rough and tumble world
and tell you right now.
And it's very, very seductive to have people like you, like the version of you that you
put on the screen.
So yeah, I mean there's a reason why I says in the scripture that neo-fights should not
be ordained or should not be teachers.
It says that in the scripture.
So we don't know better just because we have better communication technology than the apostles.
And I've watched people crash and burn who began to be ordained or to teach whatever early
on.
So that's what I think about that.
So I disagree with Father Andrew a little but we'll get there in a second.
All right.
And not just about a specific case.
So I mean, there is a general agreement in that I'm kind of famous in my parish.
You're telling Kettik-
humans that can't start a blog.
Like, I just have this rule, you can't.
People have blogs now.
Well, this was years ago.
You know that one blog.
You can't start a YouTube chat.
You can't start it.
Right, whatever you go.
And hypothetically, there would come a point where I would
let them, but nobody who's deeper into the church has asked
me yet.
So.
But this has to do with what I was talking about before.
You have to receive before you pass on.
And if you're...
do in the church especially, you're in the receiving phase.
The place where I have a little bit of disagreement,
and this is because I don't think we've done enough thinking
about a very new type of media yet,
and that's streaming.
Being a streamer is fundamentally different than having a YouTube channel
where you just record yourself, you record videos.
That's like pretty much the same thing as TV or a podcast or
Yeah.
thing. But there is now this thing, and if most over people probably are
familiar with it, don't understand it, where people will be on for hours, hours,
sometimes all day, right? Seven, eight, nine, ten, twelve hours. I know I see you on
those streams. And they're in front of a camera. And they're looking at
on the internet or play and play in video games which would do a different stuff and just
talking to their chat, their chat's communicating with them.
It's a very different type of media, right?
And the reason I think we need to do more thinking about it is that not only are there now
an increasing number of people who make a living doing this.
I don't see the strange that you could make a living doing this but you actually can.
I'm not.
Thank you.
Marvel rival's twitch stream. I make tens of dollars a year off of that
But these other folks are making a living and for example you have people who are
Orthodox or become Orthodox but that's not
Primarily what they talk about they might mention it if she says something right and I think telling them they can't write so
Yeah, and then there's other people who it's like
want to do eight hours of theology talk, right? And those are very different.
different things.
And so I think it's more a thing
where we need to do more thought about that
and come up with some really good guidelines, right?
And give people in particular say,
there were not searches good at this
about not just making some broad rule,
but even if we make a broad rule being like, okay,
well in this particular case, right?
Here's what's best and giving guidelines about, you know,
at this stage in your journey,
You could talk about this kind of thing.
And that kind of, but don't go here, here, here.
Right.
And there's a difference between, you know, interviewing people
and presenting your own material.
And we're throwing up polemics at other churches or whatever.
Yeah.
We're from other Orthodox Christians.
Right.
Yeah.
So I think it's a finer toothed comb than just saying.
Yeah, of course.
Right.
But we don't disagree.
But did you come to the part where we just won't pause it? Well, we won't go into it.
We'll detail that we need to. But there are positive things.
Can we have the internet? And as someone who is deliberately entered into this milieu to try to participate and hopefully try to do it in a positive way, though if you listen to Twitter, I'm demon possessed.
You're the world.
Yeah.
Actually, this morning it was announced that Father Stephen...
is the false prophet and that Jonathan Pazzo is the beast.
But anyone knows looking at the two of them
that Father Stephen is clearly the beast.
Definitely the beast.
And indeed his birthday is one of the numbers of the beast.
My birthday is June 16th, so it's 616.
But yeah, but so.
Nice try Twitter.
But one of the trends now is, what are the trends now
that I think is a beautiful thing is
these guys who are streaming and stuff.
for orthodox are now saying again and again,
you can't do orthodoxy on the internet.
There is no orthodox internet.
Go to liturgy.
Go to liturgy, go to liturgy, go to liturgy.
I know one streamer who has started banning people
from his chat if they're in his chat too long
without going to liturgy.
Right.
He's like, you're not gonna just sit here
and talk about orthodoxy.
You're banned until you go to liturgy.
said be a photo of you at a North of Oxford.
Wow.
and I'll let you back into the chat.
Yes, also sign letter from your priest.
So there are ways we can shape this.
It doesn't have to be a yes or a no.
There are ways we can shape this
and make it more positive.
Yeah.
This is a question, but you answer all the things.
Just listen to you.
I've been following you for a long, long time.
But at the same time, what you have taught me
And when my priest has allowed for me to do, and I perish,
it's still great, everyone, regardless.
When we became Orthodox, it was Father Gordon Walker,
who adopted me, graphically.
And he took the shyness out of me.
He said, Mirna, you're short.
Nothing, you can do about it.
You're proud.
Nothing you can do about it.
You have an accent.
You're an alien, so accepted.
Acid who you are.
So, next Sunday, you'll be the grider.
That was 40 years ago.
40 years ago.
And then the last, my crease right now.
He said, yes, you can continue doing what you're doing.
And what I'm saying is for the people who are sitting behind me pretty much, agreed
everyone regardless if they want to talk to me or not, whether they see me the way they
want to see me, it's okay.
through the past three, four, five years because growing and I have learned how
to see who they are, what they are, what they need.
And I have learned just to say, sit down,
stand up with me, that's it.
Don't pick up a book, just listen with your eyes.
You can't, you smell everything.
You will do that.
Entruder, entruder, the last few.
years, I can see that orthodoxy is aiming to the heart. But we, we the laity must be gracious,
regardless if they have tattoos coming out of their ears. I mean, it's just sometimes,
It was primal, but yet you can see that it's a Gus child.
And for me just to say hello, how are you? Sit down with me.
Are you sure?
Yes, sit down with me.
And if they want to go to coffee, I don't expect for them to do it themselves.
So for us Orthodox who have embraced the faith,
We must be givers. Just let you say.
We must be good.
Amen.
APPLAUSE
Thank you for coming, fathers.
Speaking of roles and responsibilities, I was wondering if you had any thoughts on Orthodox Christians
who are artists and writers, but not necessarily making icons or hymns or books on theology.
Yes, I have thoughts about that.
that.
In Orthodox Christianity has a long, long, long history of filling out a culture in ways that
are not just liturgical arts.
They may be related to the liturgical arts and somewhere or another, inspired by them,
influenced by them, and printed by them.
But what's interesting is, you know, like Orthodoxy in America being so relatively young,
and I know people think, well, it's been here for 200 years, that's young folks.
with an oxygen-america being relatively...
of the young, our sense of the whole of Orthodox tradition is still not entirely recovered.
We still have not received all of it for ourselves.
Like for instance, a lot of people do not know that the Byzantine era saw multiple commentaries
on Homer's Iliad written by Byzantine writers.
Our idea of what a Byzantine writer is is, well, it's Church Father's commenting on the
the medical councils or whatever and that's what we think it is.
Right, or as I like to point out to people saying,
Beasley the Great, you know, who is a sort of minor
saint that no one's ever heard of.
He has this entire.
That's why he's called the Great.
That's right.
He's got a great.
He has this entire address that he gave to students
about how to read pagan literature correctly.
Right, this idea of there's a narrow set of things
that are sanitized and good and correct,
and that's what we do.
And then...
and ignore everything outside of that,
that some people have, that's their idea
of what Orthodox Christianity is,
that is just not constant with our tradition.
Our tradition is full of all kinds of music
and literature and art that are not the kind of thing
that you would put inside a church,
but that does not make them evil.
It just means that they're a little bit lesser.
They're kind of lower down the mountains, so to speak.
and that's perfectly okay.
And indeed, that's where we spend most of our time.
Most of our time is not actually spent inside church services.
There's a whole world, I think, of possibilities for people who have these skills to do things that are truly human.
because being human is what Orthodox Christianity is about.
Right? So, for...
For instance, at the Paris Rime now attached all Saints, we just had our feast day.
And so the feast day was celebrated with pulled pork barbecue because Eastern Carolina barbecue
is the world's greatest barbecue and that's just the way that it is.
I have room in my stomach for all gods of barbecue, but Eastern Carolina is the very highest.
And then also there was Memphis people are going to attack.
I know, I know.
I just had to put that out there.
But then there were also people there kind of on the porch who were playing, fiddles and
guitars and banjos and all this kind of stuff because that's...
North Carolina culture, and it wasn't some weird alien thing. It was the appropriate thing to do on the feast day at a church that's in Central North Carolina.
And there are people who are making all kinds of art that are not liturgical art, that are it's good Orthodox stuff. It doesn't have to be preaching a sermon.
And indeed, if you try to put some kind of sermon or agenda into it often, it's very off-putting.
You know, you don't make...
Christianity better, you just make rock music worse.
That's right exactly.
To quite a phrase.
Yeah, exactly.
So I think that there is all kinds of room as orthodoxy
kind of settles in.
We're still really early in the process.
It probably won't really be settled in
till our great grandchildren.
And that's OK.
That's just where we are.
As it settles in, there's some good things to do.
And I think that this...
This art that is not liturgical art, if it's attempting,
I think if it tries to be liturgical art,
but is actually doing it badly,
like not according to the canons and traditions
of liturgical art, which I've seen that too.
And it's always very cringe.
But if it tries to be what it is,
but simply is something that is made
by someone who is an Orthodox Christian,
then it can be blessed and it can be powerful.
And...
and can show the beauty of Christ to people in a way
that they may not be able to access otherwise.
So yeah, I mean, I could go on and on about this.
But I mean, like multiple things that I work on
are about trying to read literature, for instance,
from an Orthodox point of view.
And most of the literature not written by Orthodox people,
but to still read it from an Orthodox point of view
and find ways that we can interpret it as Orthodox Christians.
And then people can also make this stuff as
well. So there's so much that can be done. So if you're one of these people that have these artistic skills
be encouraged to go forth and make, you know, and it's okay to make mistakes. That's how you make stuff that's better as you
you know, you break it a bunch of times and then
eventually once in a while you make something really amazing.
I'll just add that artists and writers and musicians are the only people we do this to
right like no one goes to an architect that is like
They're only allowed to design churches.
Right, or construction company, you can only build churches.
That's it.
That's all you can build.
Or a carpenter, you can only make crosses.
Right, like we accept with every other profession in the world that you don't have to only
do the explicitly Christian version.
But for some reason we put that onus onto writers and artists and musicians.
to me if so.
Something is beautiful, if something is true, that is its connection to God.
Indeed.
It doesn't have to be some explicit.
And something that is beautiful and something that is true is far more connected to God
than like Christian Kitch.
That's like ugly and fake.
Right.
Father.
I think one of the things that we voted against.
to people online, you should understand that nobody in this room is actually orthodox.
If you take the word and greet me correctly praising no one always correctly praises God.
I would think it would be much better when people join the church and those in the church
who would explain to them that they are trying to be orthodox because they take it as a
name instead of a reality of how do I correct
praise God all the time because when they get on the internet and they put that label on
I'm orthodox my response is no you're not orthodox you're trying to be orthodox which is
the basis of humility. Second point I want to quickly make an argument away from here when
I came here you were talking about people that left the parish I see a reality that I didn't
expect to see we're looking down the road the majority of the people in at least our
churches will be converts.
Converts need to understand it's a different cultural background of the ethnic people that were either born here or born over there.
Understand their background, understand their circumstances. We are too quick to judge them
because we don't understand where they came from or what they went through.
That empathy will do us more in learning to love one another than to become super author-authorized.
I'm a convert. I know and you don't know because you don't come to church why
They don't come to church, sit down and really talk to them and find out, you asked me,
why did I go to church?
Because my mother made me go to church until I was 18 years old.
And I got nothing out of going to church.
I rebelled.
I said I wasn't going to go to church anymore.
I told I was going to become Catholic just to get it a stop pushing me to go to church.
However the Lord took me to another parish where I really found the Orthodox church and
never look back. But if we understand where people are coming from.
would be much more able to help to guide them and to help them.
Of course, absolutely.
Hi, fathers.
Thank you for being here.
So I'm a chanter.
This may be a little bit of a scattershot question.
I can't help you.
OK, we already covered that earlier.
Regarding chanting and content on the internet,
there's kind of a little bit of a boom right now
with young men, chancers, putting themselves out
on their personal YouTube channels.
and you know, acquires and all of this.
But there's still a really big gaping hole in a lot
that you could listen to.
You know, I listen to chant at work sometimes
and there's just not a whole lot that, you know,
I can listen to or that I like.
And I kind of have mixed feelings sometimes about, you know,
maybe I love what this young man is doing,
but having a camera on you at the chant stand,
singing in front of everybody that, you know,
thousands of people can watch.
Maybe that's not good for your ego,
or maybe...
It's, you know, I don't know if people should be putting out that content, and then, but
should it just be very professional academic choirs that put out albums, you know, once
every few years, you know, as a young chanter, I might, you know, think, oh, should I start
putting stuff out there so people can hear me?
I'm just kind of, I've felt a little mixed feelings about the benefit.
and the harms of having, I guess in general,
just listening to church and chant like at work.
It's not the same thing as being in the church
and praising the Lord, sometimes just background music.
And I just was curious if you have any thoughts
about the proliferation of liturgical music online
and in general through media.
Yeah.
The very beginning of ancient faith radio was John Matic.
stripping a bunch of CDs that people at his parish had given him, and then he just started
streaming them from a laptop from his back porch in Chicago.
And but it's interesting to think about what happens when you record liturgical music.
We live in a world of recorded music.
I used to be a stage-hand, and I remember I did, usually in the summers I did lots and
lots of concerts.
And I'm sure you've all had the experience if you've been to a big concert of some pop-ear
band where the band is playing the song
everybody's familiar with, but it doesn't sound quite like it does on the album, or quite like it,
I'm sorry, quite like it doesn't Spotify. What's an album? People buy records now again.
I know, I've heard this, like, vinyl. Yeah, it doesn't sound quite the same. And the version
that everybody knows and singing along with is the version that they heard in the recording,
which is always exactly the same.
So there's something, there's a distance that's created
as a result of doing that.
And I think it's important to be mindful of that
and to realize that it creates,
there's a certain contingency to that, right?
And then it also can create problems.
Like when you're used to,
if most of the electrical music you listen to
is recorded by like professional acquires
and chancers and stuff, and then you go to church
And you don't quite have...
that professional sound, it can actually be kind of frustrating.
You know, like, oh, that was a blue note in not in a good way.
You know, so that's a difficulty there as well.
At the same time, I think that there is a benefit to having these things available for
people to access them.
Not just for sort of evangelistic purposes, but like if someone listens to the liturgical
music and they say that it helps them to get through their day.
I'm not going to tell them to stop.
But I think that, yeah, it's a new thing, right?
I mean, it used to be that there was no recorded music at all.
Like recording music did not happen.
You did not hear music unless you were in the presence of a musician playing it.
Live music was the norm, right?
And there's something about that that is quite different.
No.
Yeah, I think we still haven't quite grappled with it.
I mean, the basic question of, you know, should every
chanter be getting on the internet?
I mean, it's kind of the same question of, you know,
who should be producing content, whether they have a
prayerful approach to that, whether they are doing it
in concert with their father-convester, whether it's really
needed, you know.
Oh, look, there's another person who started a channel
or started a podcast.
You know, I say this is a guy who has started way too many podcasts.
So, yeah, I think it's part of the age that we live in, and we have to be mindful and
careful and wise as much as we can be, but realize also there's just a lot of inherent
brokenness to the media itself, and just realize, okay, well, it's never going to be perfect.
It's never going to be perfect.
But we can use it in this imperfect way to accomplish some purposes imperfectly.
And that's okay.
One of the great benefits of recorded church music
is for many people, that's how they learn,
how to do church music.
When I was in seminary,
as an anti-Yokin seminarian,
we had one person come once every month or two
and given our worth of Byzantine music instruction,
which is not enough to learn to be a Byzantine chanter,
not remotely.
I'm living proof.
But I was able to learn some things from pre-recorded stuff.
Now, of course, you can literally take classes
and Byzantine Chan and interact with a teacher through Zoom,
which, you know, one of the weird blessings
that has come from the pandemic is that kind of connectivity
for training in those things because most parishes
don't have an actually classically trained chanter
in the parish who can teach other people
how to do that stuff.
And so this kind of gives us some of this access.
But yeah, we just have to be careful.
Tell us some more stories about the days before the phonograph, grandma.
Did you know, speaking of the phonograph, I have to say this.
Thomas Edison's idea of the phonograph.
You know what he thought it was going to be used for?
He thought it would be used by most people to record their pastor's sermons
so they could listen to them at home. Not joking.
Anyway.
That didn't turn out that way. No, it did not.
No, it did not.
So yeah, I personally don't listen to a lot of
out side of church, because I get enough of that at work.
I go home and it's like Kenny Rogers, some super tramp,
maybe some fog hat.
You know, in Irish traits.
But yeah, I think there's a big difference as Father Andrew
was alluding to there at the end.
If you're posting yourself chanting online
is, are you doing it in a way where there's like an
instructional value to it? Are you teaching people about
chant? Are you helping teach people how to chant? Or are
you just trying to call attention to how good you believe you
are at chanting? Those are two different things. One of
those is about your ego and the other one is about.
Father Elias Batar, who is the person who Father Andrew was
alluding to earlier. Father Elias Batar said to us once
When you are asked to read the Epistle in Church,
you are not singing the National Anthem at a ballgame.
And he's not that far off sometimes, frankly.
At one point in a parish, I would say which one are aware,
there was a guy who would get up to do the Epistle in Arabic
and would like cover his ear, like Eddie Murphy
in the party all the time video,
Like while he's like chanting
And it turned out from some of the Arabic speaking people that he was actually using melodies
from like Arabic pop music while singing like St. Paul's Epistle to the Romans.
Right, so we had to kind of deal with that whole situation.
But that's a case where again, it sort of becomes about your ego rather than about, right,
its structural value.
is one of the key things I think not.
with music on the internet, but anything on the internet.
Yeah.
If anything becomes a vanity project, right, it needs to go.
This is why I pick on him so much on Lord of Spirits.
I don't want to let him develop vanity, even self-esteem,
really.
Right.
I'm removing that temptation from his path continuously.
Let's see, our last question.
Thank you, Father.
has been good over the-
Of course, of both days.
I think the broad contours of what I'm picking up on and asking, we go to St.
Ignatius, and we are day-loosed with people.
Well, bad.
Yeah.
And kind of this circle back around, we over-rotate so much on the intellectual content of our
catechesis.
And Miren and I have talked a lot about this.
These people coming in, and you guys talked about this to the sort of blast.
the deities of modern culture,
they don't know how to do anything.
Meir and I have talked about hospitality.
They don't know how to cook.
So we're asking people to come in
that don't even know how to be.
And I wonder if you guys could just maybe
riff a little bit more on a practical catechesis
because in many ways I feel like that's lacking.
I think that we can...
Backfill the theological content as people are healed through the love of the church.
But sometimes it's hard when we have so many people coming at us to know how to just
invite them in and love them.
And our clergy will get frustrated and people will get frustrated and just be like, why
don't they just know how to X?
And it's like they don't.
And Father Hans is really great about talking about this.
It's like the depth of the woundedness.
and vacuum that we're encountering
and the people that are coming in
has really yet to be understood.
So I wonder if you guys could just
kind of riff on that a little bit more.
How we dealing with this vast influx of people
can categorize them gently and appropriately.
Yeah.
And the place that I lived until about six weeks ago,
five weeks ago, the public library would occasionally
you call
classes that they refer to as adulting classes.
And you can imagine what, like, one was like,
here's how you keep a checkbook, right?
Here's how you check on whether and how your car needs
maintenance, you know, this kind of stuff.
And I think in a lot of ways that Orthodox Christianity
America is going to have to begin to give humaning classes
because the
the disconnection, the alienation, the father was talking about has become so pervasive now.
A friend of mine that I've done with lots of stuff with, you can say from Roland, is doing a series?
Yeah, yeah him.
Yeah.
Oh.
Rowdy Rowdy Roland.
He's doing a series of videos and it's also an audio podcast which is called How to Be in Orthodox
Christian.
And the beginning of it does not say the Orthodox Church is the second...
largest Christian communion in the world with approximately 250 million members and
it's divided into 14, 15 or 16 depending on how you count them, autosuffalo's churches,
right, which is that's the beginning of orthodoxy 101.
Someone says, what is your orthodox church, and if that's where you go, again, that's not
incorrect information.
But like his very first episode is titled, Let's Start with Maridum.
And it's kind of the prologue.
And then his first real episode is, here's how you enter a church.
So you walk in with him and you see him on the camera
and he gives you kind of a tour, actually, of the church.
But he shows you what you do.
And then the next few episodes, here's how you pray.
Here's how you fast.
Here's how you give alms.
And I believe very firmly,
having very much tried the whole orthodoxy 101 thing
myself for a long time,
that this is where a catechism needs to go.
And I knew that he did that.
And so I'm the one who basically twisted his arm to make the show.
And he says at the beginning he says, look, this is not catacism.
This is supplement to catacism that your priest might be able to use for you, if he wants,
if he feels like it's good.
And because when people are invited into that,
and to the very 3D warmth of what it means to be an Orthodox Christian,
Then they begin to form relationships with people.
and they begin to learn how to be with other people.
They begin to learn how to be loved by other people
because often they don't have sort of love receptors.
They're not trained in how to love
because they were neglected maybe when they were being raised.
And, you know, so obviously they're not gonna come in
day one and know how to do all those things.
So you just say, hey, come sit with us
and maybe they won't say anything at coffee hour,
but they'll watch everybody at the table.
talking to each other and being with each other
and eventually be like, wow, this looks great.
And maybe they'll spend a year not knowing
how to enter into that.
But the key is for people next to them say,
hey, what do you think of this?
Or tell me about your experience with this,
or where are you on this?
This kind of thing to invite them
and to ask these good, open-ended, curious questions.
Like, you can't really love somebody
if you're not curious about them.
And I think it's our in curiosity
that often prevents our loving.
other people. Like the kind of the worst, if you actually are trying to connect with somebody,
the worst thing you can say to them is, hey, how are you? Because the response to that
is always like one word or something very brief. It's designed like that whole exchange
that will script the people that we all do over and over again, is designed to be a conversation
that lasts as short as possible. How are you? Oh, fine. Good. You know, busy but good. Right?
And I actually watched a thing giving a suggestion of it.
If you want to break that, if someone says to you,
hey, how are you doing?
You can say stuff like, and this was my favorite one.
Same panic, different disco.
Because if you say something funny or unexpected like that,
then I'm waiting for funny.
Oh, sorry, thank you, father.
They laughed, they laughed.
Look, how much you're too funny.
Yeah, it was a courtesy laugh.
You would a little too emo.
A little too.
But I think that...
rather than say, hey, how are you?
To actually inquire about them in some way
that's not invasive, so what are you got going on this weekend?
What are you excited about?
What are you working on right now?
These are all good, open-ended questions
that often a lot of people have not taken
the human in-classes don't know to do that with people.
But I think that if we show that curiosity
for other people.
than that invites them in.
You know, people are attracted to people who are attracted.
So if you demonstrate interest in another person,
they become interested in what it is that you have to give them.
You know, so yeah, I think that,
I mean, in some ways evangelism is now easier than it's ever been.
You know, or I should say simpler than it's ever been,
maybe not easy but simpler.
ever been because many people coming to our doors now have little to no prior
religious experience and so you don't have to unpack it all or whatever. You just
save. Let me tell you who Jesus is and what he did and what he expects of us
and that's the gospel. You know I think the time has come. I'll be super brief.
All right.
No, just two things to sort of add.
Number one, be super patient with people.
and let them do what they need to do.
Right, if they need to sit in coffee hour for 10 minutes
and then go somewhere else to the church library or wherever
and sit by themselves for 20 minutes, let's just let them do that.
Right, just sort of let them do what they need to do.
And then when you get the opportunity,
right, in terms of these things they don't know how to do,
you say, hey, do you know how to do this?
Let me show you.
Right? And those opportunities will present themselves. Right? But you have to let a person
who's wounded and healed, you have to let them move at their own pace. You can't rush
them. You just have to be there ready, making the offer ready to do it when they're ready
to receive it. See how quick I did that? Good job.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much everybody. God bless you.
Applause.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient
Faith Radio.
And I be held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them
And was 10,000 times 10,000, than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land
that was slain to receive power and riches,
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation, chapter 5, verses 11 through 12.